A Guide to the Frederick Otto Seibel Papers, 1908-1968
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
Frederick Otto Seibel Papers, 1908-1968
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library, Virginia Commonwealth University
M 23
16.9 linear feet and oversize material
Frederick Otto Seibel
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for use without restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The original collection was a gift to the Department by Mrs. Helen McCarthy in July 1970. Additional Seibel materials were donated to the Departement and intergrated with this collection by various individuals over the years.
Biographical/Historical Information
Frederick Otto Seibel was born in Durhamville, New York, on 8 October 1886 and died in Richmond, Virginia on 19 June 1968. Siebel spent his childhood drawing sketches of the Erie Canal. He was married with no children. After Attending classes at the Art Students League in New York City for a short time. Seibel started his own commercial art business in the early years of the twentieth century. His first cartoon was printed in the Oneida Dispatch in 1908. He began his career as a cartoonist in 1916 for the Knickerbocker Press in Albany, New York. Seibel moved to Virginia in 1926 to become an editorial cartoonist for the Richmond Times-Dispatch and has been there for over thirty years. He did several shows at Metropolitan Museum Of New York, Art Institute of Chicago and Virginia Museum of Fine Arts. A biography is contained in the Spring 1977 of the Virginia Cavalcade (included in Box 1). Fred O. Seibel died in 1968 after completing nearly 16,000 cartoons. Most famous cartoon "Retreat from Moscow" (11-5-1936) depicting presidential candidate Alfred E. Smith as Napoleon after FDR's landslide victory in 1936.
Scope and Content Information
The Seibel Collection is comprised of two major sections: letters which Seibel received relating to his newspaper cartoons (including correspondence from Harry Truman, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Robert Kennedy, Barry Goldwater, Harry F. Byrd, John L. Lewis, J. Edgar Hoover and numerous members of the federal and state government), and a complete set of his published cartoons from both the Knickerbocker Press and the Richmond Times-Dispatch. Other items in the collection include drawing notebooks and early art school sketches, seven oil paintings thought to have been painted by Seibel, folios containing copies of sketches by Charles Dana Gibson and Frederic Remington, as well as folios containing newspaper clippings of major world events in Seibel's lifetime. There are also thirty-four original cartoons, some of which were autographed by Seibel.
Arrangement
Arrangement
Collection is arranged alphabetically.
Organization
The Special Collections and Archives Department has 34 Original Cartoons, some inscribed, Seibel's own clipping file, early drawings, oils and watercolors and some correspondence. The collection is divided into two groups: Seibel's oil paintings, folios, and oversized cartoons are stored separately; the newspaper copies of his cartoons and boxed in groups of fifty and are arranged, with few exceptions, chronologically. The cartoons were cut and numbered by Seibel in the order in which they were published, and that numerical order has been preserved.
Contents List
- Biography Virginia Cavalcade, Spring 1977 (Box-folder 1.1)
- Yearbook (Oneida High School) 1908 (Box-folder 1.2)
- German Notebook (Box-folder 1.3)
- School exercise book (Box-folder 1.4)
- Notebook, various topics (Box-folder 1.5)
- Notebook 1912-1919 (Box-folder 1.6)
- Notebook 1912-1921 (Box-folder 1.7)
- Notebook of quotations (Box-folder 1.8)
- Notes on caricature and cartooning 1915 (Box-folder 1.9)
- Nags Head materials (Box-folder 1.10)
- Commemoration booklet of assassination of McKinley (Box-folder 1.11)
- Miscellaneous newsclippings (Box-folder 1.12)
- Ephemera (Box-folder 1.13)
- Correspondence: Crow Letters (Box-folder 1.14)
- Correspondence: Byrd, Harry F., Sr. 1926-1949 (Box-folder 1.15)
- Correspondence: Byrd, Harry F., Sr. 1950-1962 (Box-folder 1.16)
- Correspondence: A 1922-1952 (Box-folder 1.17)
- Correspondence: B 1916-1955 (Box-folder 1.18)
- Correspondence: C 1924-1954 (Box-folder 1.19)
- Correspondence: D 1921-1951 (Box-folder 1.20)
- Correspondence: E 1917-1952 (Box-folder 1.21)
- Correspondence: F 1910-1950 (Box-folder 1.22)
- Correspondence: G 1904-1965 (Box-folder 1.23)
- Correspondence: Goldwater, Barry 1965 (Box-folder 1.23a)
- Correspondence: H 1919-1959 (Box-folder 1.24)
- Correspondence: Hoffa, James R. 1959 (Box-folder 1.24a)
- Correspondence: Hoover, J. Edgar 1940 (Box-folder 1.24b)
- Correspondence: I 1938 (Box-folder 1.25)
- Correspondence: J 1930-1956 (Box-folder 1.26)
- Correspondence: K 1916-1961 (Box-folder 1.27)
- Correspondence: Kennedy, Robert F. 1961 (Box-folder 1.27a)
- Correspondence: L 1933-1949 (Box-folder 1.28)
- Correspondence: M 1929-1956 (Box-folder 1.29)
- Correspondence: N 1919-1952 (Box-folder 1.30)
- Correspondence: O 1935-1940 (Box-folder 1.31)
- Correspondence: P 1917-1958 (Box-folder 1.32)
- Correspondence: R 1931-1967 (Box-folder 1.33)
- Correspondence: Roosevelt, Franklin D. 1930 (Box-folder 1.33a)
- Correspondence: S 1930-1959 (Box-folder 1.34)
- Correspondence: T 1930-1967 (Box-folder 1.35)
- Correspondence: Truman, Harry S. 1954 (Box-folder 1.35a)
- Correspondence: U 1932-1940 (Box-folder 1.36)
- Correspondence: V 1931-1947 (Box-folder 1.37)
- Correspondence: W 1916-1949 (Box-folder 1.38)
- Correspondence: Y 1935-1937 (Box-folder 1.39)
- Correspondence: Z 1937-1938 (Box-folder 1.40)
- Fred Seibel name plate for desk (Box-folder 1a-1)
- Two Wrva phonographs-recording of Seibel (Box-folder 1a-2)
- Audio Tape of Interview with Seibel, n.d. (Box-folder 1a-3)
- Articles with mentions of Seibel's name 1913 (Box-folder 1a-4)
- Graphic Advertisement for Seibel (Box-folder 1a-5)
- Advertisements for Bustles, Cigarettes, Hammocks, Flour, Etc..., 1890s (Box-folder 1a.6)
- Cartoonists Who Helped Win the War 1919 (Box-folder 1a.7)
- Cartoons: Knickerbocker Press 1908-1919 (Box-folder 2.1-2.32)
- Cartoons: Knickerbocker Press 1919-1926 (Box-folder 3.1-3.33)
- Cartoons: Richmond Times Dispatch 1926-1929 (Box-folder 4.1-4.24)
- Cartoons: Richmond Times-Dispatch 1929-1933 (Box-folder 5.1-5.26)
- Cartoons: Richmond Times-Dispatch 1933-1937 (Box-folder 6.1-6.26)
- Cartoons: Richmond Times-Dispatch 1937-1941 (Box-folder 7.1-7.29)
- Cartoons: Richmond Times-Dispatch 1941-1946 (Box-folder 8.1-8.29)
- Cartoons: Richmond Times-Dispactch 1946-1950 (Box-folder 9.1-9.28)
- Cartoons: Richmond Times Dispatch 1950-1954 (Box-folder 10.1-10.26)
- Cartoons: Richmond Times-Dispatch 1954-1959 (Box-folder 11.1-11.27)
- Cartoons: Richmond Times-Dispatch 1959-1965 (Box-folder 12.1-12.26)
- Cartoons: Richmond Times-Dispatch 1965-1968 (Box-folder 13.1-13.15)
- The Hogarth Drawing Tablet 1898 (Box-folder 14.1)
- The Hogarth Drawing Tablet 1898 (Box-folder 14.2)
- Imperial Drawing Tablet 1899 (Box-folder 14.3)
- Preliminary of Preacademic Certificate 1903 (Box-folder 14.4)
- Loose Newspaper Articles 1913 (Box-folder 14.5)
- Orson Lowell Prints 1913 (Box-folder 14.6)
- Political Advertisements 1916 (Box-folder 14.7)
- The Thomas School of Aviation Booklet 1916 (Box-folder 14.8)
- Unidentified Advertisements 1916 (Box-folder 14.9)
- Keystone Co./Oneida Co. 1916 (Box-folder 14.10)
- Miscellaneous Advertisements 1916 (Box-folder 14.11)
- Clothing Advertisements 1916 (Box-folder 14.12)
- Seibel Advertising Cards, 1916 (Box-folder 14.13)
- Charles D. Gibson Articles and Prints 1905-1944 (Box-folder 14.14)
- Scrapbook, Pulitzer Prize Competition 1951, oversize (Map-case 22.1)
- Cartoons fetured in the Syracuse Herald 1930s, oversize (Map-case 22.2)
- Original Political Cartoons 1917-1944, oversize (Map-case 22.3)
- Original Political Cartoons 1917-1919 (Box-folder 22.4)
- Original Political Cartoons 1931-1968, oversize (Map-case 22.5)
- Bed Advertisements 1916, oversize (Map-case 22.6)
- Citizens Trust Company Posters, Community Silver Advertisement 1916, oversize (Map-case 22.7)
- The Pratt Church Co., Frankfort, NY 1916, oversize (Map-case 22.8)
- Eagle Beers Poster 1916, oversize (Map-case 22.9)
- L.C. Smith and Bros., Typewriters, Avertisement 1916, oversize (Map-case 22.10)
- Loyal Order of the Moose Poster 1916, oversize (Map-case 22.11)
- Luncheon for 1st M.E. Church of Albany 1919, oversize (Map-case 22.12)
- Oneida Poster, oversize (Map-case 22.13)
- Seibel Calendars 1932-1933, oversize (Map-case 22.14)
- Stittville Products Poster 1916, oversize (Map-case 22.15)
- UMC Steel-Lined Shot Gun Shells, Utica's Dollar Day Advertisement 1916, oversize (Map-case 22.16)
- Prints by A.B. Frost 1904, oversize (Map-case 22.17)
- Prints by Charles D. Gibson 1900, oversize (Map-case 22.18)
- Prints by Frederick Remington 1904, oversize (Map-case 22.19)
- Prints by Henry J. Peck, E.W. Kemble, R. Van Buren, Crook 1900, oversize (Map-case 22.20)
- Prints by James Montgomery, oversize (Map-case 22.21)
- Architectural Drawing, Drawings of miscellaneous buildings, NY, oversize (Map-case 22.22)
- Character Sketches, n.d., oversize (Map-case 22.23)
- Drawing of President McKinley 1902, oversize (Map-case 22.24)
- Miscellaneous Canvases, Sketches, and Watercolors, oversize (Map-case 22.25)
- Portraits, n.d., oversize (Map-case 22.26)
- Seibel Self Portrait, n.d., oversize (Map-case 22.27)
- Sketches of Venus de Milo, Discus Thrower, and other Classical Sculptures 1907, oversize (Map-case 22.28)
- Sketches of Classical Sculptures 1907, oversize (Map-case 22.29)
- Sketch of Three Boats, n.d., oversize (Map-case 22.30)
- Sketch of Abe Lincoln, n.d., oversize (Map-case 22.31)
- Sketches of Famous Busts 1902, oversize (Map-case 22.32)
- Sketches of Hands and Feet, n.d., oversize (Map-case 22.33)
- Collier's Weekly, San Francisco Fire 1906, oversize (Map-case 73.34)
- Cover Pages from Harper's Weekly 1871-1879, oversize (Map-case 73.35)
- Famous Headlines Newspapers: Battleship Maine, Peary to the North Pole, Sinking of the Titantic 1898, 1909, 1912, oversize (Map-case 73.36)
- Miscellaneous Newspapers 1915-1917 (Map-case 73.37)
- Newspaper Clippings from Seibel-Anderson Wedding, n.d. (Map-case 73.38)
- Newspapers featuring Obituaries of Theodore Roosevelt; Franklin Roosevelt 1910, 1933, oversize (Map-case 73.39)
- Newspapers featuring John F. Kennedy Assassination November 23, 1963, oversize (Map-case 73.40)
- Newspapers featuring V-E Day August 15, 1945, oversize (Map-case 73.41)
- Newspapers featuring Calvin Coolidge 1933, oversize (Map-case 73.42)
- Newspapers featuring Obituaries of Woodrow Wilson; British Royal Family 1924, 1936, oversize (Map-case 73.43)
- New York Tribune, The Sun Newspaper 1910-1920, oversize (Map-case 73.44)
- Newspapers from WWI 1917-1919, oversize (Map-case 73.45)
- Puck March 8, 1882, oversize (Map-case 73.46)
- Undated Prints from Puck, oversize (Map-case 73.47)
- Undated Issues of Puck, oversize (Map-case 73.47a)
- Chicago Tribune features of 16 Historic Front Pages 1865-1933, oversize (Map-case 73.48)
- Images of George Washington, Map of Tidewater, Copy of Declaration of Independence, Prints of Napoleon, oversize (Map-case 73.49)
- Political Posters for: Zandon, Knox, McKinley, Roosevelt, FDR, Sherman, Taft 1901-1936, oversize (Map-case 73.50)
- Harbor Photograph, oversize (Map-case 73.51)
- Scottish Rite Membership Certificate, The Imperial Council of the Ancient Arabic Order of the Nobles of the Mystic Shrine 1927, 1934, oversize (Map-case 73.52)
- Advertisements Mounted to Brown Paper, oversize (Map-case 73.53)
- Portrait of an Unknown Woman, oversize (Map-case 73.54)